Guide to the Gertrude Raffel Schmeidler Papers, 1943-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gertrude Raffel Schmeidler papers 1943-1983
Schmeidler, Gertrude Raffel
30.8 linear feet Extent: circa 24,000 items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.01147
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gertrude Schmeidler Papers were given to the Duke University Library by Dr. Schmeidler in 1987. Copyright interests in these papers have not been transferred to the University.
Biographical Note
1912, July 15 Born Long Branch, New Jersey
1932 B.A. magna cum laude Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1932-1933 Statistical assistant at Foundation for Neuro-Endocrine Research
1933 M.A. Clark University, Worcester, Mass.
1935 Ph.D. Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1935-1937 Instructor at Monmouth College, Long Branch, New Jersey
1937 Married Robert Schmeidler
1942-1944 Research Associate at Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1945-1985 Taught in the Department of Psychology, City College of the City University of New York
1945-1946 Research Officer at the American Society for Psychical Research, New York
1945 Published article, "Separating the Sheep from the Goats," in the Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research
1949-1955 Consultant at Barnard College, New York
1958 Co-author of the work ESP and Personality Patterns, with Dr.Robert A. McConnell
1959 President, Parapsychological Association
1964 Earned the William McDougall Award for Distinguished Work in Parapsychology, established by the Parapsychology Laboratory at Duke University
1969 Edited Extrasensory Perception
1971 President, Parapsychological Association
1976 Edited Parapsychology: Its Relation to Physics, Biology, Psychology and Psychiatry
1977 Associate Editor of Wolman's Handbook of Parapsychology
1981-1985 President, American Society for Psychical Research
1988 Published book Parapsychology and Psychology: Matches and Mismatches
Collection Overview
The Gertrude R. Schmeidler Papers span the period 1943-1983. The bulk of the collection consists chiefly of Research Files but also includes Correspondence and Writings. The research data located in the Research Files consists primarily of information which Schmeidler gathered through her work with students and colleagues as an experimental psychologist and parapsychologist. This data formed the basis of her published journal articles and books about how various factors and traits affect a person's extrasensory perception (ESP) abilities. There are very few personal papers located in the collection.
The value of the collection may be viewed from several perspectives. One is able to see how researchers collaborate with each other; to evaluate the value of networking and mentoring; to study the role of women in parapsychology; and to become aware of groups and institutes interested in the study of ESP, such as the American Society for Psychical Research, the Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory, and the Parapsychology Foundation, Inc.
Reflected in much of the research is the work for which Schmeidler is most notable, the development of the metaphor of the sheep and goats. She determined through several cycles of ESP card-guessing experiments that "sheep" (persons who believed that success was possible in ESP tasks) scored higher than "goats" (those who rejected the possibility of success). Later documentation in the sheep/goat research includes data and correspondence by Murray Melnick and Christopher Scott pertaining to their study of earlier tabulations of Schmeidler's sheep/goat research.
The following correspondents, researchers, and subjects are generally represented throughout the Correspondence and Research Files Series. Included are: Gardner Murphy, Schmeidler's mentor and the person who first interested her in psychical research; Ingo Swann, who studied PK (psychokinesis) effects on temperature; Caroline Chapman, a psychic with whom Schmeidler conducted proxy settings; Eileen Garrett, a psychic who was president of the Parapsychology Foundation Inc., and with whom Schmeidler conducted proxy settings; Steve Heyman, who studied the effect of time and impatience on ESP abilities; Betty Humphrey, who worked in the Duke Parapsychology Laboratory in the late 1940s and early 1950s and used drawings as her ESP targets; Larry Lewis, who attempted to find out if ESP hones into a target like sonar; and Thelma Moss, who studied a house haunting. Schmeidler collaborated with Swann, Heyman, Lewis, and Moss on the research topics listed above and co-authored journal articles which were published as a result of their research. Schmeidler also published an article about her proxy settings with Chapman. The research data relating to the Garrett settings was never published. There is scattered correspondence between Schmeidler and J. B. and Louisa Rhine, but not a substantial amount. There are several letters between J. G. Pratt, who was working at the Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory, and Schmeidler pertaining to the Chapman proxy settings in the mid 1950s. There are numerous letters between Schmeidler and Humphrey, some describing the working environment at the Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory; others relate to Humphrey's research. Other topics are represented primarily in the Research Files Series, including data about how various attitudes, conditions, traits, and surroundings affect ESP abilities. Among them are frustration, utilizing Saul Rosenzweig's Picture Frustration Study; Rorschachs and ESP scores of patients suffering from cerebral concussions; background stimuli; Rorschachs and ESP scores in maternity patients; ESP and memory; ESP scores following psychotherapy; and mood and attitude as predictors of ESP performance; telepathic rapport based on personality traits; and others such as long distance experiments in telepathy, precognition, poltergeists, and clairvoyant medical diagnosis based on the Silva Mind Control method.
The data for experiments, both successful as well as unsuccessful, are in the collection. The results of some were never reported in the literature. Because of the amount of data in the collection, it is possible that some of the experiments could be replicated and/or studied for new results.
The Writings Series primarily consists of information pertaining to the work she co-authored with Robert A. McConnell, ESP and Personality Patterns.
Folders throughout the collection contain Schmeidler's typed notes which describe the data, list the name of the researcher with whom she collaborated, and in some cases the article or articles which resulted from the research. Others indicate the nature and subject of the correspondence and include information pertaining to her various writings.
Through Schmeidler's correspondence with colleagues world-wide and her collaboration with fellow scientists, one is able to gain an understanding of the vast range of experiments and topics studied in the parapsychological field. One is also able to study the difference in research styles between Americans and Europeans. Since the research files span a period of forty years, the collection also reflects the various methods, materials, and equipment used for research in the field.
Related collections in the Department include the Parapsychology Laboratory Records and the Louisa Rhine Papers.
Subject Headings
Murphy, Gardner, 1895-1979; Swann, Ingo, 1933-; Garrett, Eileen Jeanette Lyttle, 1893-1970; Heyman, Steve; Humphrey, Betty, M.; Pratt, J. Gaither (Joseph Gaither), 1910-1979; McConnell, Robert A.; Scott, Christopher; Melnick, Murry; Chapman, Caroline; Moss, Thelma; Lewis, Larry; American Society for Psychical Research (1906- ); Duke University. Parapsychology Laboratory; Parapsychology Foundation; Extrasensory perception -- Research; Parapsychology -- Research; Psychical research; Mediums; Ghosts; Rorschach test; Telepathy; Precognition; Poltergeists -- Case studies; Clairvoyance; Psychokinesis; Rosenzwieg picture-frustration test; Women parapsychologists; Women college teachers -- New York
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series
  - 1943-1968, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1971-1972, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1973-1974, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1974, July-1983, undated (Box 5)
  - Garrett, Eileen, 1953-1955, undated (Box 5)
  - Murphy, Gardner, 1951-1974, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Ozanne, Charles E., 1953-1956 (Box 5)
- Writings Series
  - ESP and Personality Patterns (Box 6)
  - ESP and Personality Patterns: Response to Criticism (Box 6)
  - Personal Values and ESP Scores (Box 6)
  - 1953-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Research Files Series
  - Rorschach Tests
    - 1944-1945, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1945-1946, Mar.,Murphy, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1946, Mar., schmeidler-Hunter (Box 9)
    - 1946, Summer, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1946, Summer-Fall, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1946-1951 and undated (Box 10)
    - 1946-1951, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1947, Spring, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1947, Spring-Fall, (7 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1947, Fall, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1947-1950, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1948-1949, Spring, (5 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1949, Spring/Fall-1950, Spring, (7 folders) (Box 15)
    - 1950, Spring-Fall, (4 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1950, Feb.,Inspection Records: Sheep and Goats, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1951, Spring, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1951, Feb.,Inspection Records: Sheep and Goats, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1951-1956 (Box 17)
    - 1951-1956, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1955-1956, Fall, (4 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1956, Fall-1958, Spring, (5 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1958, Spring/Fall-1960, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1959-1961, Fall, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1961-1966, Fall, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - Various dates, and undated, (3 folders) (Box 24)
    - Chase and Wladkowsky, undated (Box 24)
    - Erkstein, undated (Box 24)
    - Inspection Records, 1943, 1946, undated (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous data, undated (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous: (Box 25)
    - Preselected on Basis of ESP Scores, 1945-1947, 1970, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - TAT analysis, undated (Box 25)
  - Sheep/Goat
    - ESP Record Sheets: 1941, Aug.-1946, Mar., (7 folders) (Box 25)
    - ESP Record Sheets: 1946, Apr.-1946, July, (7 folders) (Box 26)
    - ESP Record Sheets: 1946, July-1947, Spring, (8 folders) (Box 27)
    - ESP Record Sheets: 1947, Sept.-1948, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - ESP Record Sheets: 1949, Apr.-1951, Apr., (9 folders) (Box 29)
    - ESP Record Sheets: (Box 30)
      - 1951, May (Box 30)
      - Various dates and undated, (2 folders) (Box 30)
      - Sheep/Goats, undated, (2 folders) (Box 30)
      - undated, (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - ESP Record Sheets: undated, (6 folders) (Box 31)
    - ESP Record Talley Sheets: 1948-1949, undated, (4 folders) (Box 32)
    - ESP Record Sheets and Related Materials (Box 33)
      - 1946, Nov. (Box 33)
      - 1954-1956, Fall, (5 folders) (Box 33)
    - ESP Record Sheets and Related Materials, 1959-1960, undated, (6 folders) (Box 34)
    - ESP Record Sheets and Related Materials, undated, (5 folders) (Box 35)
    - Rorschach Tests: 1948, Fall-1949, Spring, (5 folders) (Box 36)
    - Rorschach Tests: (Box 37)
      - 1949, Spring (Box 37)
      - Various dates (Box 37)
    - Rorschach Tests: Inspection Records:
      - 1946, Sept.(Hunter) (Box 37)
      - 1947, Feb.-1948(Sheep/Goats), (5 folders) (Box 37)
    - Rorschach Tests: ESP Scores, Pairs: 1946-1955, (6 folders) (Box 38)
    - Student Responses: (Box 39)
      - 1946, July-1949, Fall, (8 folders) (Box 39)
      - Various dates and undated, (2 folders) (Box 39)
    - Student Responses: undated, (8 folders) (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 41)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Extra Scores and extra subjects, undated., (2 folders) (Box 41)
      - Gimore-Melnick Data (Box 41)
      - Pictures, undated (Box 41)
      - Research data from ESP work on Sheep/Goats--Cohen, 1959 (Box 41)
      - Schmeidler, City College--Eckstein's Class on Abnormal, Apr. 5, 1946 (Box 41)
      - Sheep/Goat Classification Response to Christopher Scott, (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Subjects
    - Agent: ESP Data, undated (Box 42)
    - Agent: Percipient Experiment Instructions (Box 42)
    - Agent: Percipient Experiment (Box 42)
    - Agent: Percipient Experiment: (Box 42)
    - Agent: Attempts at objective Rorschach classification (Box 42)
    - Agent: ESP Data, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 42)
    - Allen - TAT (Box 42)
    - American Society for Psychical Research, 1946 (Box 42)
    - American Society for Psychical Research: Pictures (Box 42)
    - American Society for Psychical Research: Pictures, (2 folders) (Box 43)
    - Background stimuli and ESP responses, 1983, (3 folders) (Box 43)
    - Bainow - TAT, undated (Box 44)
    - Barry, H., MacKinnon, P. W., Murray, H.A.: Experimenter Files (Box 44)
    - Bickman, Leonard: Honors Research (Box 44)
    - Blaustein Targets, 1944 (Box 44)
    - Booklets of Values, 1952, (3 folders) (Box 44)
    - Bridge to ESP target: tests (Box 45)
    - Brier, Robert and Barry Savits: Silva Mind Control, three Experiments in Clairvoyant Diagnosis, (4 folders) (Box 45)
    - Bullen, undated (Box 45)
    - Card guessing experiment (letters to people about) 1963 (Box 45)
    - Census of some unusual experiences (Box 45)
    - Chapman, Caroline (Proxy Sessions), (5 folders) (Box 46)
    - Chapman, Caroline (Proxy Sessions) (Box 47)
    - Chase, Stanley: Data (Box 47)
    - Chi Square Test (Box 47)
    - Children and reincarnation (Box 47)
    - Clairvoyant, Kykeshoorn, M.B. (Box 47)
    - Clock cards, 1982, (3 folders) (Box 47)
    - Cognition class: City College of the City University of New York (Box 48)
    - Concussion Patients and Hospitalized controls data, Rorschachs and ESP scores (Box 48)
    - Crystal Images: data (Box 48)
    - Drawings
      - 1946, July 31, (2 folders) (Box 48)
      - Clairvoyance, (2 folders) (Box 48)
    - Drawings: (Box 49)
      - Clairvoyance (Box 49)
      - Moonfaces, (2 folders) (Box 49)
      - Moonfaces and interest tests (Box 49)
      - Moonfaces--Duke--1946 and City College of the City University of New York, 1947 United States of America (Box 49)
    - Ehrenwald, Jan: PSI: Questionnaire (Box 49)
    - Ehrlich, Data (Box 49)
    - Eilbert, L.'s MA thesis: published with Schmeidler, 1950, (2 folders) (Box 49)
    - ESP: (Box 50)
      - Card type experiment (Box 50)
      - Contest (Box 50)
      - Data, 1951, 1955 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 50)
      - Scores in maternity patients (Box 50)
      - Memory test, (2 folders) (Box 50)
    - ESP: Memory test, (2 folders) (Box 51)
    - ESP Records: Confidence check and scored, 1958, (3 folders) (Box 51)
    - Feedback in ESP, (2 folders) (Box 51)
    - Feedback in ESP, (4 folders) (Box 52)
    - Feedback paper test data, (2 folders) (Box 52)
    - Feedback paper test data, (2 folders) (Box 53)
    - Feedback with ESP symbols: A Failure to Replicate (Box 53)
    - Free Association, (2 folders) (Box 53)
    - Friedneberg, William and P. Males: Data (Box 54)
    - Friedman, Ronald M. and E. D. Dean: Mood and ESP Correlation (Box 54)
    - Garrett, Eileen (Proxy Sessions), (4 folders) (Box 54)
    - Garrett, Eileen (Proxy Sessions) (Box 55)
    - Goodrich, Joyce: Psychic Healing (Box 55)
    - Grady tests/interpretation (Box 55)
    - Group experiments: Extra results, undated (Box 55)
    - Hand Test Protocols, 1974 (Box 55)
    - Haunted House: Data, 1966 (Box 55)
    - Heyman, S.:
      - Data for Paper, 1976 (Box 55)
      - Data for Time Metaphors and ESP, 1965 (Box 55)
    - Heyman, S.: Data for Time Metaphors and ESP, 1965, (5 folders) (Box 56)
    - Heyman, S.: Data for Time Metaphors and ESP, 1965, (3 folders) (Box 57)
    - Hudesman, J.:
      - Clock Card Data, (2 folders) (Box 57)
    - Hudesman, J.: Clock Card Data, (5 folders) (Box 58)
    - Hudesman, J.: Clock Card Data (Box 59)
    - Hudesman, J. and G. Schmeidler: ESP scores after psychotherapy sessions (Box 59)
    - Humphrey, Betty:
      - Data (Box 59)
      - Scoring of 4-picture clairvoyance tests, 1947, Dec. (Box 59)
    - Introversion and ESP (Box 59)
    - Jensen, Donald: Psychical abilities, 1974 (Box 59)
    - Kopler: TAT and ESP Data, 1945 (Box 60)
    - Korn: Data (Box 60)
    - Kornfeld: TAT (Box 60)
    - Kreiman records, 1978 (Box 60)
    - LeShan, L.: Boby Image related to ESP scores (Box 60)
    - Lewis, Larry:
      - Data (Box 60)
      - Data for EEG-ESP research paper, (2 folders) (Box 60)
    - Lewis, Larry: Feedback in ESP, Part II (Box 61)
    - Lowy, Grace: Data (Box 61)
    - Lutzky: Data on children (Box 61)
    - Memory tests: Word lists (Box 61)
    - Metaphor Research, 1962-1963, (2 folders) (Box 61)
    - Mind-reading interpretations (Box 61)
    - Mood-in-group study, (2 folders) (Box 62)
    - Moods and ESP (Canada):
      - Correspondence (Box 62)
      - Group 1-3: 1971, Feb.-Mar. 8, (3 folders) (Box 62)
    - Moods and ESP (Canada): Miscellaneous (Box 63)
    - Moss, Thelma: ESP records and letters (Box 63)
    - Moss, Thelma and Schmeidler: Haunting investigation, (2 folders) (Box 63)
    - Murphy, Gardner:
      - Creativity: ESP Project (Box 63)
      - Rorschach interpretations, 1944 (Box 63)
    - Names as target: Research, 1984 (Box 63)
    - O'Keefe, Eileen: Data (Box 63)
    - Osis, Karlis: ESP, 1955 (Box 63)
    - Out of body experiences: Questions and data (Box 63)
    - Perception "in mind's eye", (7 folders) (Box 64)
    - Perception "in mind's eye", (8 folders) (Box 65)
    - Personality of PSI experiments: Student Evaluations, 1981, (2 folders) (Box 66)
    - Picture-Frustration Records, 1946-1948, (6 folders) (Box 66)
    - Picture-Frustration Records, 1948-1949, (5 folders) (Box 67)
    - Picture-Frustration Records, 1949, (5 folders) (Box 68)
    - Picture-Frustration Records (Box 69)
      - Spring, 1950-1951, (2 folders) (Box 69)
      - 1st Group experiment, 1945 (Box 69)
      - 2nd Group experiment, 1945 (Box 69)
      - Chase and Wladkowsky, 1946 (Box 69)
      - Female, 1948 (Box 69)
      - Spring, Hunter group experiment, 1946 (Box 69)
    - Picture and A-S reaction studies (Box 69)
    - Pictures used for testing, Fall, 1956 (Box 69)
    - PK effects on temperature, (7 folders) (Box 70)
    - PK effects on temperature (Box 71)
    - PK effects on temperative: further analysis (Box 71)
    - Poltergeists:
      - Beck case, correspondence (Box 71)
      - Case studies (Box 71)
      - Case study, projective tests (Box 71)
      - Precognition: dream data (Box 71)
      - Precognitive clairvoyance, Part I (Box 71)
    - Precognitive clairvoyance, Part I and II, (2 folders) (Box 72)
    - Precognition experiment (data of first), 1961, Fall, (3 folders) (Box 72)
    - Precognition subjects record sheets, 2nd experiment (Box 72)
    - Precognition test, 1974 (Box 72)
    - Psychics (Box 72)
    - Psychokinesis on water, 1974 (Box 72)
    - Psychometry tests (Box 72)
    - Random vs Pseudorandom targets: Data, 1981 (Box 72)
    - Rasch, W. D.: Handwriting analysis, 1953 (Box 72)
    - Retkinski data: ESP, 1964, Spring (Box 72)
    - Retkinski-data, ESP: 1964, Spring (Box 73)
    - Retkinski-Replication, ESP: 1964, Gall (Box 73)
    - Retkinski: Work before going to Duke, 1964 (Box 73)
    - Salience-Group experiments (Box 73)
    - Sensory deprivation test (Box 73)
    - Sensory deprivation test (Box 74)
    - Short Story: various test scores (Box 74)
    - Soal, S. G.: ESP tests, 1956 (Box 74)
    - Steelman, J: Data, (2 folders) (Box 74)
    - Streber, K: Data (Box 74)
    - Subject record sheets and tabulations (Box 74)
    - Subject record sheets and testing specifications (Box 74)
    - Survival research questionnaires, (2 folders) (Box 74)
    - Tanagras: Telepathy research, 1946-1947, (3 folders) (Box 75)
    - Tarot card readings: Unpublished data (Box 75)
    - TAT: ESP scores, (3 folders) (Box 75)
    - TAT: ESP scores (Box 76)
    - TAT scores (Box 76)
    - Telepathy in Dyads: Data (Box 76)
    - Time estimates by psychics (Box 76)
    - Time metaphor test (Box 76)
    - Training subjects to judge free responses
      - Ruth Reinsel for N. Sondow's Ganzfeld, (2 folders) (Box 76)
      - Janet's non-blind list of correspondences: F, G, H (Box 76)
    - Visual imagery and creativity (Box 76)
    - Windholz, George: (Box 77)
      - ESP data, (3 folders) (Box 77)
      - Intercultural comparisons of expressive movements (Box 77)
    - Word association (Box 77)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1970-1971 (Box 77)
    - undated, (2 folders) (Box 77)
    - undated, (3 folders) (Box 78)
    - Tests (Box 78)
    - Unidentified data, (2 folders) (Box 78)
- Miscellaneous Series
  - 1952-1974 and undated (Box 78)
  - Colleagues' opinions about parapsychology, 1976 (Box 78)
  - Coursework assignments, 1973-1977 (Box 78)
  - Coursework exams, 1972-1979 (Box 78)
- Oversize Materials
  - Contains research files, including sheep/goat and topical research data (Oversize-box 79-81)
  - Contains subject research file: Precognition Clairvoyance (Opaperfolder Folder 1)